Guide to the Youth Document Durham and Durham Works Project Records, 1995-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Project Files Series, 1995-2006 and undated, (6 boxes)
  - Exhibits and Projects Subseries, circa 1998-2006, (3 boxes)
    - In My Community: Documenting Changing Lives In Durham, large paper reproductions of photographic print, 2000, (16.5 x 23.5 in.) (Opaperfolder 1)
      Unknown photographer. May have been used in exhibit. Prints, one negative, one positive, show the same image of lone figure with turban on grassy corner.
    - Raised Voices exhibit, 2001, (1 of 2 folders) (Box 62)
    - Raised Voices exhibit, 2001, (2 of 2 folders) (Box 63)
    - Youth Power exhibit, 2002 (Box 63)
    - Through Rebel Eyes exhibit, 2003 (Box 63)
    - Student work, 2004 (Box 63)
    - Final projects, 2005 (Box 63)
    - Moving in the 991: Bull City Bus Stories exhibit, 2005 (Box 63)
    - Final projects, 2006 (Box 63)
  - Participant Release Forms Subseries, 2000-2006
    Folders contains release forms signed by participants' parents or guardians, permitting the participants to enroll in the program, travel to designated activity sites, and have their work published and reproduced by the Center for Documentary Studies. The file is not a complete record of all participants. The forms are arranged chronologically.
    - Participant release form files (Box 63-64)
  - Program Documentation Subseries, 2000-2005, (2 boxes)
    Folders house color prints and negatives of photographs shot by the program staff throughout the course of the Youth Document Durham program each year. The photographs document various meetings, group events, and the activities of program participants. Folders arranged chronologically by year.
    - Program documentation files (Box 64-65)
  - Publications Subseries, 1995-1999, (2 boxes)
    Student-produced bound booklets drawn from their projects. Booklets contain mostly interview transcriptions but also include photographs, drawings, annotations, and poetry. Also included is a collection of Youth Document Durham participant photos and essays, edited by Hong-An Truong and published in 2005. Materials arranged chronologically.
    - Remembering the Past, Living in the Present, Focusing on the Future, 1995 (Box 65)
    - A Place Of Their Own, 1996 (Box 65)
    - Remembering the Past, Living in the Present, Focusing on the Future, 1996 (Box 65)
    - The Crest Street Community Presents Community Stories, 1997 (Box 65)
    - The Impact of Tobacco on East Wilson, 1997 (Box 65)
    - Live, Learn, Move On, 1997 (Box 65)
    - West End Memoirs, 1997 (Box 65)
    - The Connection Program Oral History Project in Five Points, Durham, NC, 1998 (Box 65)
    - Crest Street Community Stories, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Faith Stories, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Juntos Con Nuestra Herencia, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Let's Talk Tobacco, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Listen For Change, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Southwest Central Durham Representin' Like What!, 1998 (Box 66)
    - Life As We See It, 1999 (Box 66)
    - Youth Document Durham, A Five Year Retrospective, 2005, Hong-An Truong, ed. (book and promotional flyer) (Box 66)
- Additions Series, 1997-2004, (7 boxes)
  Includes materials from accession 2011-0178, and is arranged by program: Youth Document Durham, Durham Works, Connect Program, Youth Treatment Court, and Community Stories. Formats include project records, printed materials, student zines, photographic prints, negatives, slides, digital and analog recordings, and electronic project record files. Titles of photographic prints are original.
  [Electronic records have not been migrated to a library server. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
  - Connect Program, 1997-2000 (Box 67)
    - Old Five Points projects, undated (Box 67)
    - Negatives, 1997 and undated, (2 folders) (Box 67)
    - Slides, 1997-1999, (2 folders) (Box 67)
    - Negatives, 1997-1999 (Box 67)
    - Prints, 1998 (Box 67)
    - North Carolina Lambda Youth Project, February 1999, (2 folders) (Box 67)
    - Prints, Fall 2000 (Box 67)
  - Community Stories (Box 68)
    - Negatives, Fall 1999-Spring 2000 (Box 68)
    - Life As We See It booklet, 1999 (Box 68)
    - Neighborhood Stories photographs and negatives, 1997 and undated (Box 68)
    - Oral History Project collection of interviews with citizens in the Wilson Community, Summer 1997, (20 audio cassettes) (Box 68)
    - Community Stories 2, undated, (Hi8 cassette) (Box 68)
    - WVNC, produced by Leda Hartman, 1997 July 28, (1 audio cassette) (Box 68)
    - E.K. Powe Exhibit/Community Stories curriculum, (1 floppy) (Box 68)
    - Community Stories, 1999, (1 zip disk) (Box 68)
  - Youth Document Durham (Box 69)
    - Student zines, (3 folders) (Box 69)
    - Color prints and negatives, 2000 (Box 69)
    - Raised Voices: Educator's Guide, 2001-2001 (Box 69)
    - Durham schools survey data, 2003 and undated (Box 69)
    - Pictures, 2005 (Box 69)
  - Durham Works
    - Curriculum, 2000 (Box 69)
    - Youth training materials, 2001 (Box 69)
    - Binder, Fall 2000, (3 folders) (Box 69)
    - Students' jobs pamphlets (Box 69)
    - Edison Johnson, Fall 2003 (Box 69)
  - Youth Treatment Center
    - Court, 2003 (Box 69)
    - Truth Be Told curriculum, 2003 (Box 69)
    - Dasan Massenberg, 2003 and undated (Box 69)
    - Afterschool, Fall 2003 (Box 69)
    - 2004, (2 folders) (Box 69)
    - P.R.O.U.D., 2004, (2 folders) (Box 69)
  - Youth Document Durham and Durham Works audiovisual and electronic materials (Box 70)
    - Exhibit news clips, 2001, (3 VHS) (Box 70)
    - Final presentations "News Report," 2001 July 26, (1 VHS) (Box 70)
    - Jobs that Pay, 2001, (2 VHS) (Box 70)
    - Session 1 High-Tech-Cultural, 2002, (1 VHS) (Box 70)
    - "Raised Voices," 2003, (1 VHS) (Box 70)
    - Media broadcast, 2003, (1 VHS) (Box 70)
    - Healthcare interviews, 2004, (6 mini-discs) (Box 70)
    - Family interviews, 2004, (11 mini-discs) (Box 70)
    - Duke Democrats, 2004, (2 mini-discs) (Box 70)
    - Vox Populi, 2004, (2 mini-discs) (Box 70)
    - Teen stereotypes, 2004, (1 mini-disc) (Box 70)
    - Dasan materials, 2004, (4 mini-discs) (Box 70)
    - Proud celebration, 2004, (1 mini-disc) (Box 70)
    - NPR interview, 2002, (1 mini-disc) (Box 70)
    - Final Presentations, 2001 July 26, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Exhibit, 2002 Jan. 10, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Advisory meetings, 2002, (2 mini-DVs) (Box 70)
    - Interviews, 2002, (5 mini-DVs) (Box 70)
    - Raw footage, 2002, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Media news, 2001, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Session 1 Final Projects, 2002, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Session 2 presentation, 2000, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Jobs that Pay, 2001, (1 mini-DV) (Box 70)
    - Who Wants to be an Expert?, 2000, (1 audio cassette) (Box 70)
    - Final presentation, 2000, (1 audio cassette) (Box 70)
    - Jobs that Pay, 2001, (2 audio cassettes) (Box 70)
    - Why Teens Fight, 2001, (1 audio cassette) (Box 70)
    - Through Rebel Eyes, 2003, (2 audio cassettes) (Box 70)
    - Rosey Truong Youth Power, 2002, (1 floppy) (Box 70)
    - "Let's Talk About It" youth evaluations, undated, (1 floppy) (Box 70)
    - Session 2, 2002, (1 CD) (Box 70)
  - Awards
    - Two plaques honoring Youth Document Durham (Box 70)
  - Youth Document Durham Prints, 2000 (Box 71)
    8x10, 8x7, 5x7, and 3.5x5 inch prints created by students in the Youth Document Durham program.
    - Girl Listening to Headphones in a Store (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Tree Line with Police Tape (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Girl Threatening Another With an Ice Pick (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Two Security Guards Smiling (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Cordless Phone on the Charger (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Tropical Exotic Fruit Poster (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Man with Violin on the Sidewalk (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Three People in a Recording Studio (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Talking Toy Parrot with Microphone (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Man in Studio with Headphones around his Neck (8x10) (Box 71)
    - Panoramic View of a Stripmall (4 8x7 prints) (Box 71)
    - Cooking Ingredients (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Pita Shaped Like a Face (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Family Portrait (3.5x5) (Box 71)
    - Welcome Techno-Durham (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Group of People in Skullcaps Performing Inspection (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Two-Story White House (5x7) (Box 71)
    - John Frederick Educational Technology Complex (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Inside an Old Building (5x7) (Box 71)
    - SWAT Team Program Education Future Now (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Salsa (5x7) (Box 71)
    - Hush Puppies (5x7) (Box 71)
  - Youth Document Durham Prints, 2002 (Box 71)
    Prints are approximately 7x9 inches. Many are manipulated photography images and include the student's commentary on social, political, or cultural events. Titles are original.
    - Drug Use Statistics (Box 71)
    - Free Palestine (taken by Jonathon Pattishall) (Box 71)
    - Photography (taken by Lician Hernandez) (Box 71)
    - Man in Shirt and Tie in the Mall (Box 71)
    - Smoothest, Shiniest, Most Computer Enhanced Hair (Box 71)
    - Shoe Collection (Box 71)
    - Portrait of Family Portraits (taken by Marcus French) (Box 71)
    - Single Candle Flame (Box 71)
    - Black Nikes with White Check (Box 71)
    - Stairwell Shot (taken by Lazarren McLean) (Box 71)
    - Backstage Pass to Brutality (Box 71)
    - Men on Couch (taken by Gabby Torres) (Box 71)
    - House in Wooded Area (taken by Manish Pal Kaur) (Box 71)
    - Open Road (taken by Amina Cliette) (Box 71)
    - Taking Tests in School (Box 71)
    - Don't Blame it on Islam (Box 71)
    - Think Style. Think Sweatshops. Think Nike. (Box 71)
    - Unmade Bed (taken by Brianna Bagley) (Box 71)
    - Man on Phone Reading Children's Book (Box 71)
    - Look Who's Watching (Box 71)
  - Youth Document Durham Prints, 2001 (Box 72)
    Prints are approximately 8x10 or 5x7 inches. Many are manipulated photography images and include the student's commentary on social, political, or cultural events. Titles are original.
    - Woman Giving Presentation (5x7) (Box 72)
    - Room with TV in Foreground and Open Door in Background (taken by Aaron J. Garcia, 5x8) (Box 72)
    - Two Faces, Merged (4 images, 5x7) (Box 72)
    - Kids Jumping in Living Room (taken by Lena Eckert-Erdheim, 5x7) (Box 72)
    - Kids Around a Pool Table (taken by Lena Eckert-Erdheim, 5x7) (Box 72)
    - Boy on Porch with Face in Hands (5x7) (Box 72)
    - Smiling Children (taken by Lena Eckert-Erdheim, 5x7) (Box 72)
    - Interlocked hands (5x7) (Box 72)
    - Spray Painted Train Cars (5x7) (Box 72)
    - Two Faces, Merged (2 images, 5x7) (Box 72)
    - Woman on the Phone (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Tomato Plants (8x10) (Box 72)
    - End Table with Painting of a Child Peering into a Bowl (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman in White Coat Sitting on a Couch (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Schoolkid from the Innocent Lil' School (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Kid Adopting Thug Persona (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Toy Sailboat (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Ankles Bound by Rope (8x10) (Box 72)
    - I'm Really Nice if You Give Me a Chance (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Back Up Out My Face You Don't Know Me (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Whatever I'm Smart Don't Mess with Me (8x10) (Box 72)
    - I'm Smart and Smooth! I'm Nice (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Girl with Book: Whatever (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Girl with Butterfly Wings (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Girl Playing Outside (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Toy Sailboat (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Ankles Bound by Rope (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Old Man in Front of Garbage Truck (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Doctor's Office with a Wall of Diplomas (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Duke Career Center Presentation (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Unoccupied Living Room (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman Being Approached Unknowingly from Behind (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman in Front of Pond, Ripples in Background (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Singing: My Life (8x10) (Box 72)
    - I See Myself Working Hard (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Office Chair with Sweater Draped Over It (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Duke Chapel (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman in Black Business Suit Laughing (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Inside a Bank (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Le Heritage Expressions Dance Troupe (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Doctor Sitting in a Chair Talking (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Desktop Computer with Sticky Notes (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Stained Glass Window (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Family Walking Away from Camera (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Family Outside on a Dirt Road (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Asian Lunch Cuisine (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Dairy Farm Stores, now La Vaquita Taqueria (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman with Dog in Yard (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Two Men Giving a Statement (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Two Children Playing in Yard (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Students in a Courtroom (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Man in Washateria (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Household Appliances (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Dodge Pick-Up and Grill Outside of Home (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Stone House (taken by Manish Pal Kaur, 8x10) (Box 72)
    - Supper on the Stove (taken by Manish Pal Kaur, 8x10) (Box 72)
    - Office Worker in Foreground Looking at Man in Backgroun (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Cabin in a Field (8x10) (Box 72)
    - Woman Alone on Porch (taken by Lician Hernandez, 8.5x5.5) (Box 72)
    - Hispanic Family Standing on Train Tracks (taken by Edith Balleza, 9x6) (Box 72)
    - Woman in Glasses and Headwrap in Classroom (9.5x6.5) (Box 72)
    - Smiling Children (taken by Lena Eckert-Erdheim, 7x5) (Box 72)
  - Youth Document Durham Prints, 2000-2001 (Box 73)
    11x14 inch prints taken by students in the Youth Document Durham program. Titles are original.
    - Vegetables in a Cardboard Box, 2000 (Box 73)
    - Cabbage Cooked on the Stove, 2000 (Box 73)
    - Homemade Cross in Front of a Field, 2000 (Box 73)
    - Kid with Mohawk Driving, 2001 (Box 73)
    - Woman Beside Car Outside of House, 2001 (Box 73)
    - House with Wrought Iron Railings, 2001 (Box 73)
    - B.B. Gun, 2001 (Box 73)
- Alternate Listing by Project Title
  In the original arrangement as received, the projects files in the Interviews Series were arranged in folder number order rather than by project, and that original order has been retained. This alternate listing groups box numbers by project title.
  - Behind the Veil, Boxes 3, 9, 10-11, 14-20, 23, 27 (Box 73)
  - Community Stories, Boxes 1-3, 36, 39, 43 (Box 73)
  - Community Stories - West End, Boxes 35-36 (Box 73)
  - Crest Street, Boxes 3, 12, 23, 26-29 (Box 73)
  - Crest Street/Old Five Points, Box 19 (Box 73)
  - Crime Beat, Boxes 36-37 (Box 73)
  - Cultural Collage, Boxes 49-52 (Box 73)
  - Durham Eats, Boxes 34-36 (Box 73)
  - Durham Works, Boxes 37-43, 53 (Box 73)
  - Durham Works - Edison Johnson Recreation Center, 2002, Box 53 (Box 73)
  - Durham Works - Githens Middle School, 2002-2003, Box 52 (Box 73)
  - Durham's West End, Boxes 6, 17, 20-21, 32 (Box 73)
  - Faith Stories, Boxes 26, 29-30, 33-34 (Box 73)
  - High Tech World, Boxes 50-51 (Box 73)
  - Jobs that Pay, Boxes 45-48, 53 (Box 73)
  - Mercy Hospital, Boxes 3, 6-9, 11-12, 14-15, 18, 22-23, 34 (Box 73)
  - Old Five Points, Boxes 3-6, 17-18, 21-23, 26-27, 31-32 (Box 73)
  - Sounds of the City, Boxes 1, 39 (Box 73)
  - Student Practice, Boxes 15, 17 (Box 73)
  - Summer Training, Boxes 9, 17-18, 25 (Box 73)
  - Summerton, S.C, Boxes 4, 8, 9, 11-13, 17, 20-23, 26 (Box 73)
  - SWCD, Boxes 24-26, 30-32 (Box 73)
  - Techno-Durham, Boxes 37, 39, 43 (Box 73)
  - Tobacco Talk, Boxes 1, 3, 18, 21, 23-25, 28, 30-32, 34, 53 (Box 73)
  - West End, Boxes 3, 22 (Box 73)
  - Why Teens Fight, Boxes 47-49, 53 (Box 73)
  - Wilson, Boxes 9-10, 14-17, 19, 23, 32 (Box 73)
  - World Wide Colors, Boxes 44, 46-47 (Box 73)
  - Youth Forum on Media, Box 53 (Box 73)
  - Youth Power, Boxes 49-51 (Box 73)